A Guide to the Accounts of Moore, Robinson & Co, 1813-1884
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Accounts of Moore, Robinson & Co 1813-1884
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
38-47
12 volumes.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift, Essex County Court House, 1931.
Scope and Content
All but one of these ledgers seem to have belonged to the Robinson family. Primarily, they contain the accounts of John W. Robinson and his son, John B. Robinson, who operated a farm, "Gwynfield," and a general store at Centre Cross in Essex County, Virginia, as well as the administration of the estate of J. W. Robinson by his sons, J. B. Robinson, and by Harry Clay Robinson, of "River Vew," also located in Essex County. Of particular interest is the family record contained in the Farm Book (item 13). There are scattered references to African Americans throughout the set.
Contents List
- Ledger - general merchandise accounts, indexed 1813-1835 (Volume [1])
  1
- Household expenses 1848, 1862-65 (Volume [1])
- Inventory and accounts of J. B. Robinson's administration of his father's estate 1864 (Volume [1])
- Miscellaneous notes and accounts (Volume [1])
- Farm book, Gwynfield, Essex Country 1843 (Volume [2])
- Personal accounts, and accounts of J. B. Robinson as administrator of his father's estate 1862-1864 (Volume [2])
  This volume contains many entries pertaining to slaves, especially: List of slaves who "left for the Yankees" (1862-1863); List of deaths among slaves at Gwynfield (1862-1864); List of slaves working at Gwynfield (1863); Division of slaves at River View (1864) [part of J. W. Robinson's estate?]
- Account journal of J. Saunders & Co., a general merchandise firm in Loretto, Virginia 1851-1854 (Volume [3])
- Miscellanous accounts of J. W. Robinson 1855 (Volume [4])
- Miscellaneous accounts of J. B. Robinson and H. C. Robinson, largely records of the administration of the estate of J. W. Robinson 1863-65, 1868, 1870 (Volume [4])
- Invoice book of Moore, Robinson & Co. 1857 Apr.-1858 May (Volume [5])
- Stock inventories, list of open accounts, notes received, and credits 1858 (Volume [5])
- Draft advertisements for a house for rent 1866 (Volume [5])
- Daybook of Moore, Robinson & Co. 1857 (Volume [6])
- Inventories of stock 1857-1858 (Volume [6])
- Accounts re: estate of J. W. Robinson 1862 (Volume [6])
- Accounts of J. B. Robinson as administrator of his father's estate 1865, 1867, 1868 (Volume [6])
- Daybook of Moore, Robinson & Co., including board accounts and miscellaneous notes 1857 Apr.-Dec. (Volume [7])
- Account journal of Moore, Robinson & Co. 1857 Apr.-Dec. (Volume [8])
- Fifteen memorandum books containing J. B. Robinson's accounts and notes 1857-1884 (Volume [9])
  The first twelve books include notations re: the operation of Gwynfield Farm, as well as accounts of the administration of J. W. Robinson's estate. Also recorded are Freedmen's accounts for laborers at Gwynfield and notes on crops and plantings. The last three books contain diverse notes and records.
- Daybook of Moore, Robinson & Co., including accounts (1859) of sundries, memos re: open accounts, and a list of notes due 1858 Jan.-Oct. (Volume [10])
- Account journal of J. B. Robinson 1858-1859 (Volume [11])
  including notes on open accounts (1859); inventory (1862) of personal property in the estate of J. W. Robinson; and accounts (1862-64) as administrator of his father's estate.
- Farm book, including notes on harvests, chicken and stock production, personal accounts, and employee records 1866-1867 (Volume [13])
  Also contains family record of the children of J. W. Robinson and Mary E. B. Dickinson.